Guide to the Meteorological Manuscripts Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Meteorological Manuscripts Collection
1821-1943
MS 349
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
An artificial collection of meteorological observations, journals and records kept by Joseph William Bennett (1811-1883), George Dutton (d.1857), Oscar L. Hargar (1843-1887), Benjamin Franklin Harrison, Alfred Shepard Monson (1795-1870), William Charles Redfield (1789-1857), William Maxwell Reed (b.1871), Charles Rich (1809-1862), Minerva Wing, and others, relating to the climate and weather conditions primarily in Connecticut, 1821-1943. Some oversize materials relate to additional states, as well as to European countries.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Some oversize materials are fragile and may require conservation work before use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Elias Loomis, 1883; H. A. Newton, 1870; James H. Craig, 1924; Henry White, 1860, John Reader, 1957, and others.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by individual.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of meteorological observations, journals and records kept by Joseph William Bennett (1811-1883), George Dutton (d.1857), Oscar L. Hargar (1843-1887), Benjamin Franklin Harrison, Alfred Shepard Monson (1795-1870), William Charles Redfield (1789-1857), William Maxwell Reed (b.1871), Charles Rich (1809-1862), Minerva Wing, and others, relating to the climate and weather conditions primarily in Connecticut, 1821-1943. Some oversize materials relate to additional states, as well as to European countries.
Meteorologists -- Connecticut; Meteorology; Science; New Haven (Conn.) -- Climate; Bennett, Joseph William, 1811-1883; Dutton, George, 1802 or 1803-1857; Harger, Oscar, 1843-1887; Harrison, Benjamin Franklin, 1811-1886; Munson, Alfred Shepard, 1795-1870; Redfield, W. C. (William C.), 1789-1857; Reed, W. Maxwell (William Maxwell), 1871-1962; Rich, Charles, -1862; Wing, Minerva
- Inventory, (1821-1883)-1943; 2 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Bennett, Joseph William (1811-1883)
    - "Meteorological Journal kept at New Haven," Conn, 1849-1850 (Box 1)
    - "Weather Journal," New Haven, Conn.: 15 vol.s, 1852-1869 (Box 1)
    - "Weather Journal," New Haven, Conn.: 15 vol.s, 1852-1869 (Box 2)
  - Dutton, George (d. 1857): "Registry of Tides and Winds," Fort Taylor, Key West, 1847-1852 (Box 2)
  - Harger, Oscar L. (1843-1887): weather recordings in Oxford, Conn., and elsewhere, 1857-1883 (Box 2)
  - Monson, Alfred Shepard (1795-1870): "Observations of the Thermometer," New Haven, Conn., 1821-1854 (Box 2)
  - Redfield, William Charles (1789-1857)
    - "Record of Storms," 1494-1859, Undated (Box 2)
    - "Meteorological Journal" (or "Register," or "Record"), New York: 15 vols.; last one, for New York and Philadelphia, is by his son John Howard Redfield (1815-1895), 1831-1861 (Box 2)
    - "Meteorological Journal" (or "Register," or "Record"), New York: 15 vols.; last one, for New York and Philadelphia, is by his son John Howard Redfield (1815-1895), 1831-1861 (Box 3)
    - "Meteorological Journal" (or "Register," or "Record"), New York: 15 vols.; last one, for New York and Philadelphia, is by his son John Howard Redfield (1815-1895), 1831-1861 (Box 4)
    - "Meteorological Journal" (or "Register," or "Record"), New York: 15 vols.; last one, for New York and Philadelphia, is by his son John Howard Redfield (1815-1895), 1831-1861 (Box 5)
    - [attributed]: "Philosophical Lectures," vol.s 2-3, Undated (Box 5)
  - Reed, William Maxwell (1871-): "Will Next Summer be Hotter than Last Summer?": carbon of typescript, [1943?] (Box 5)
  - Rich, Charles (1809-1862): "Meteorological Journal," New Haven, Conn.; continued by Edward Claudius Herrick (1811-1862), 1838-1843 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified
    General note
    Folio
    - "Record of Observations on the Weather at Windham, Conn.", 1932 (Box 5)
    - "Meteorological Register," New, York, 1854-1855 (Box 5)
    - Weather observations, 1855-1865 (Box 5)
    - Meteorological charts (photographs), 1870-1875, undated (Box 5)
    - Wing, Minerva: meteorological observations, West Charlotte, Vermont, 1873 (Folder 6)
- Oversize
  Scope and Contents
  Oversize items have been boxed up by size; box numbers in listing are not necessarily sequential.
  - Roll 1 [7 items]
    - "Fluctuations of the Barometer on Mt. Washington and at Portland Me.", 1872 September- 1874 October (Box 7)
    - "Mt. Washington Barometer", 1874 November- 1877 August (Box 7)
    - "Fluctuations of the barometer at Pike's Peak and Denver." and "Pike's Peak and Colorado Springs", 1873 December- 1877 December (Box 7)
    - "Pike's Peak Barometer" (also Sacramento), 1870 September-1878 September (Box 7)
    - "St. Bernard" (graphs), 1858 January- 1860 December (Box 7)
    - "St. Bernard. Colle di Valdobbia" (graphs), 1877 January- 1879 December (Box 7)
    - "Valdobbia" (graphs), 1879 January- 1881 December (Box 7)
  - Roll 2 [14 items]
    - Seven pages of handwritten text on lows between the equator and 30° N latitude, Undated (Box 7)
    - "Storm tracks between the equator and 30°N latitude" (7 maps), Undated (Box 7)
  - Roll 3 [10 items]
    - Annotated maps of the North Atlantic - observations, 1870 January 29-1878 February 8 (Box 7)
  - Roll 4 [2 items]
    - Annotated map of the United States - observations, 1874 April 11 (Box 7)
    - Annotated map of North America, the Atlantic Ocean and Europe, 1874 March 5- March 18 (Box 7)
  - Roll 5 [1 item]
    - Annotated map of North America, the North Atlantic and Europe, 1875 January 19- February 3 (Box 7)
  - Roll 6 [2 items]
    - Annotated map of the United States - Mean Temperatures, 1872-1873 (Box 10)
    - Annotated Map of the United States, 1872 October 19- October 21 (Box 10)
  - Roll 7 [1 item]
    - "Wallingford Observations" - Dr. Benjamin Franklin Harrison, 1858 (Box 8)
  - Roll 8 [1 item]
    - "Wallingford Observations", [1859?] (Box 8)
  - Roll 9 [3 items]
    - "Thermometer" - Annotated United States map, 1872 December 24 (Box 10)
    - "Thermic Isabnormals" - annotated United States map, 1873 June 18 (Box 10)
    - Annotated map of the Northern Hemisphere - observations, Undated (Box 10)
  - Roll 10 [17 items]
    - United States map annotated with observations
      - N.y. Dec 14 - Dec 26 (Box 10)
      - N.y. Dec 16 - Dec 28 (Box 10)
      - N.d. (Box 10)
    - "War Department Weather Map" (with daily readings) [14 items], 1871 April 21-September 8 (Box 10)
  - Roll 11 [6 items]
    - Weather observations (U.S. locations), 1874 (Box 9)
    - Weather observations (U.S. locations) [2 items], 1872 September (Box 9)
    - Portland, Oregon. Weather observations, 1872 September- December (Box 9)
    - Portland, Oregon. Weather observations, 1873 January- March (Box 9)
    - Pressure curves/West Indies and Mexico - Observations, 1874 December- 1879 October (Box 9)
  - Roll 12 [1 item]
    - Annotated map of New Haven Harbor, Undated (Box 9)
  - Roll 13 [1 item]
    - Weather observations (graphs) of points in the United States, 1873 April-November (Box 7)
  - Roll 14 [6 items]
    - "Calms" - Annotated U.S. maps [5 items], 1873 December 17-December 19 (Box 10)
    - "Chart of Calms", 1872 September 2- 1874 October 21 (Box 10)
  - Roll 15 [2 items]
    - "Fluctuations of the Barometer at Santa Fe" (graph), 1873 November- 1875 January (Box 7)
    - Annotated U.S. map "Calms", 1873-1877 (Box 7)
  - Roll 16 [1 item]
    - Annotated "Hypsometric Map" - U.S., 1877 (Box 10)
    - U.S. map "Showing frequency of storm centers", Undated (Box 9)
  - Roll 18 [8 items]
    - Annotated War Department Weather Maps, 1872 November 4-November 29 (Box 9)
  - Roll 19 [4 pieces]
    - "Fluctuations of the Barometer on Mt. Washington", 1873 January 18- June 18 (Box 9)
    - "Hourly fluctuations of the barometer at the summit and base of Mt. Washington", 1873 June 10- June 17 (Box 9)
    - "Fluctuations of the barometer at the summit and base of Mt. Mitchell, NC", 1873 August 6- September 5 (Box 9)
    - "Fluctuations of the barometer at the summit and base of Mt. Washington, NH", 1873 May- June (Box 9)
    - "Fluctuations of the barometer at Mt. Washington", 1873 May 9- May 24 (Box 9)
  - Roll 20 [1 item]
    - Unidentified, annotated observations, [1861?] (Box 8)
  - Roll 21 [1 item]
    - Unidentified, annotated observations, 1859 (Box 8)
  - Roll 22 [1 item]
    - Unidentified, annotated observations, Undated (Box 8)
  - Roll 23 [1 item]
    - "Wallingford observations/Dr. Benjamin Franklin Harrison", 1858 (Box 8)
  - Roll 24
    - Observations west of 92° longitude [note book and papers], 1878 (Box 8)
  - Roll 25 [6 items]
    - Weather observations from points in the U.S. [4 items], 1872 October- 1874 September (Box 9)
    - "Pressure curves in the region of the Rocky Mountains", 1874 August- October (Box 9)
    - "Barometric Curves in the region of the Rocky Mountains", 1873 December- 1874 July (Box 9)
  - Roll 26 [3 items]
    - Observations at Mt. Washington and Mt. Mitchell, 1873 May- September (Box 9)
    - "U.S. Signal Service Chart" showing observations by Albert J. Meyer, 1872 June- 1873 May (Box 9)
    - "Rainfall and barometric oscillations" - Paris, 1871 May-1874 October (Box 9)
  - Roll 27 [1 item]
    - "Rainfall (daily average) of the London District", 1813-1872 (Box 9)
  - Roll 28 [2 items]
    - "International Simultaneous Weather Map" [7:00 A.M. Washington time, #188 template], Undated (Box 10)
    - French map, 1874 October 22 (Box 10)
  - Roll 29 [4 items]
    - "Rainfall chart of the United States" [made for the Smithsonian Institution], 1879 December-1880 December (Box 10)